大家好，我是Dan Boneh ，很高兴大家来听我的密码学课程
Hello, my name is Dan Boneh, and I'd like to welcome you to my course on cryptography
这个学季我将在斯坦福大学教授这门课程。我尝试
that I'll be teaching at Stanford University this quarter. This quarter, I'm experimenting
将课程录成下来，以便同学们在网上观看
with recording the lectures and having the students watch the lectures online.
事实上，欢迎任何人来观看我的视频并加入我们的课程
In fact, anyone is welcome to watch the lectures, and join the course.
这是一个实验，所以让我们看它进行得如何。
This is an experiment, so we'll see how it goes. My goals for this
这门课程主要是讲授密码学基本原型是怎样工作的
course are basically to teach you how cryptographic primitives work.
但更重要的是，我要教你们如何正确的使用密码学原型
But more importantly I'd like to teach you how to use cryptographic primitives correctly
以及推导构建加密机制的安全性，我们将会看到各种各样
and reason about the security of your constructions. We will see various
抽象的密码学原型，还会做一些安全性证明
abstractions of cryptographic primitives, and we'll do some security proofs.
我的目标是在课程结束后，你们能够推导加密机制的安全性
My goal is that by the end of the course you'll be able to reason about the security of cryptographic
能够破解不安全的加密机制
constructions and be able to break ones that are not secure.
关于我希望你们怎么上这门课，简单说两句，首先
Now I'd like to say a few words on how I would like you to take the class. First of all,
我非常推荐你们上课做笔记，所以我真的
I'm a big believer in taking notes as you listen to the lectures. So I would really
鼓励大家用自己的话总结归纳并记下笔记
encourage you to summarize and take notes in your own words of the material that's being presented.
提醒一下，录像的讲课速度相对于正常的课程会快很多
Also I should mention that on the videos, I'm able to go much faster
所以我建议大家
than I would go in a normal classroom. And so I would encourage you to
periodically pause the video and think about the material that's being covered
经常性地暂停视频，思考讲课内容
and not move forward until the material is clear in your mind. Also from time to time,
直到弄清楚了之后再继续
the video will pause and pop-up questions will come up.
偶尔视频自动暂停，会有弹出问题
These are intended to kinda help you along with the material, and I would really encourage you to answer
它们是帮助大家理解讲座内容的
those questions by yourselves rather than skip them. Usually the questions
我鼓励大家自主回答这些问题而不是跳过他们
are about the material that has just been covered, and so it shouldn't be too difficult to answer
通常这些问题都是关于刚刚讲过的内容，所以解答这些问题并不难
the questions. So I would really encourage you to do them rather than skip them.
我真的建议你们去解答它们而不是略过它们
Now, by now I'm sure everybody taking the class knows that cryptography is used
现在，我确信上这门课的大家都知道密码学在计算机领域无处不在
everywhere computers are. It's a very common tool that's used to protect data.
它是用来保护数据的常用工具
For example, web traffic is protected using a protocol called HTTPS.
例如，网站流量是使用HTTPS协议保护的
Wireless traffic, for example, Wi-Fi traffic is protected using the, WPA2
无线流量，例如WiFi，是使用WPA2保护
protocol, that's part of 801.11i. Cell phone traffic is protected
WAP是801.11i的一部分，手机流量是使用GSM加密机制保护的
using an encryption mechanism in GSM. Bluetooth
traffic is protected using cryptography,
蓝牙流量是使用密码学保护的，等等
and so on. We're gonna see how these various systems work. In fact, we're gonna
我们将看到各种各样的系统是怎样工作的
cover SSL, and in fact, even 802.11i in quite a bit of detail. And you'll see how
实际上，我们还将介绍SSL，802.11i的一些细节
these system work in practice. Cryptography is also used for protecting files
你们将会看到这些系统实际应用上是怎么工作的
that are stored on disc by encrypting them. So if the disc is stolen,
密码学也可以用来加密保护在硬盘上的文件，如果硬盘被盗
the files are not compromised. It's also used for content protection. For example
文件也不会被窃取，这也适用于保护内容。例如
when you buy DVDs and Blu-Ray disks, the movies on these disks are encrypted, in
当你买DVD和或者蓝光碟时，光盘上的电影将被加密
particular DVD uses a system called CSS, the Content Scrambling System, CSS, and
DVD使用的是CSS加密系统，也叫内容扰乱系统
Blu-Ray uses a system called AACS. We'll talk about how CSS and AACS work.
蓝光碟使用的是AACS加密系统，我们将介绍CSS和AACS是如何工作的
It turns out that CSS is a fairly easy system to break.
事实证明CSS是很容易被破解的系统
And we'll talk about how, we'll do some cryptanalysis and actually show how to break encryption that's used in CSS.
我们将学习如何破解CSS系统，对CSS中使用的密码系统进行分析和破解
Cryptography is also used for user authentication and in many, many, many
密码学也可以被用来做用户认证
other applications that we'll talk about in the next segments.  Now I wanna go back
在接下来的我们讨论的非常多的应用中。
to secure communication, and talk about the case where, here, we have a laptop
现在让我们谈回保密通信，讨论这种情况：我们有一台笔记本电脑
trying to communicate with a web server. This is a good time to also introduce our friends,
正尝试与网络服务器通信，这是一个介绍我们朋友们的好机会
Alice and Bob, who are gonna be with us throughout the quarter. Essentially Alice
Alice和Bob，他们将陪我们度过整个学季
is trying to communicate securely with Bob. Here Alice is on the laptop and Bob
Alice总是想要和Bob进行安全通信，Alice在笔记本的一端
is on the server. The protocol that's used to do that is called HTTPS, but in fact,
Bob在服务器的一端，使用的协议是HTTPS协议，但其实
the actual protocol is called SSL. Sometimes it's called TLS.
实际使用的协议是SSL，有时也被叫做TLS
And the goals of these protocols is to basically make sure that as this data travels across the
这些协议的目的是确保数据在网络传输时
network, an attacker first of all can't eavesdrop on this data. Second of all, an
首先，攻击者无法窃取数据
attacker can't modify the data while it's in the network. So no eavesdropping and no tampering.
其次，攻击者不能再修改数据，即无窃听，无篡改
Now as I said the protocol that's used to secure web traffic called TLS
现在我们来谈谈我们用来保护网页安全的TLS
actually consists of two parts. The first part is called the handshake protocol
它由两部分组成，第一部分称为握手协议
where Alice and Bob talk with one another and at the end of the handshake
Alice和Bob相互交谈，在握手的最后
handshake basically a shared secret key appears between the two of them. So both
双方共享一个密钥
Alice and Bob know this secret key, but an attacker looking at the conversation has
所以Alice和Bob双方都知道这个密钥，观察这个通信的攻击者
no idea what the key K is. Now, the way you established your secret key, the way
不知道这个会话的密钥k。现在，建立密钥的过程
you do the handshake, is using public key cryptography techniques, which we're gonna talk
握手过程，都用到了公钥密码技术，这个我们将在
about in the second part of the course. Now once Alice and Bob have the shared key,
课程的第二部讨论。现在一旦Alice和Bob共享了密钥
you can use this key to communicate securely by properly
你可以使用这个密钥安全通信，恰当地
encrypting data between them. And in fact this is gonna be the first part of the course,
加密他们相互传递的数据。事实上，这就是本课程的第一部分
which is essentially once the two sides have a shared secret key, how do they use
也就是双方共享共享密钥后，
that secret key to encrypt and protect data that goes back and forth between them?
怎么使用密钥加密并保护通信数据
Now, as I said, another application of cryptography is to protect
正如我所说，密码学的另一个应用是用来保护
files on disk. So, here you have a file that happens to be encrypted, so that even
硬盘上的文件。现在你有一个已加密文件
if the disk is stolen, an attacker can't actually read the contents in the file.
即使你的硬盘被偷了，攻击者也不能读取硬盘中的文件内容
And, if an attacker tries to modify the data on disk, the data in the file while
如果攻击者试图修改磁盘上的数据，
it's on disk, when Alice tries to decrypt this file, that will be detected, and
当Alice试图解密文件时，改动会被检测出来
she'll then basically ignore the contents of the file. So we have both
Alice便会忽略文件内容
confidentiality and integrity for files stored on disk. Now I want to make a minor philosophical
所以我们能保证存在磁盘的文件的保密性和完整性，这里有一点哲学的东西
point, that in fact storing encrypted files on disk is very much the same
事实上，在硬盘上储存加密文件
as protecting communication between Alice and Bob. In particular, when you
和Alice和Bob保密通信类似。尤其是
store files on disk, it's basically Alice who stores the file today wants to read
当在磁盘上储存文件时，基本上Alice保存的是明天还要看的文件
the file tomorrow. So rather than communicating between two parties Alice and Bob,
所以与Alice和Bob两方间的通信不同
in the case of a stored disk encryption, it's Alice today who is
所以对硬盘储存文件加密的是今天的Alice
communicating with Alice tomorrow. But really the two scenarios, secure
和明天的Alice通信，但这两种情形：
communications, and secure files, are kind of philosophically the same. Now, the
安全通信和安全文件，从哲学上来说是一样的
building block for securing traffic is what's called symmetric encryption
以分组的形式保护流量的技术叫做对称式加密
systems. And we're gonna talk, in the first half of the course extensively about
在本课的第一部分，我们将详细介绍对称加密机制
symmetric encryption systems. So in a symmetric encryption system, basically, the two parties,
所以在对称加密机制中，
Alice and Bob, share a secret key k, which the attacker does not
Alice和Bob共享密钥k，攻击者不知道密钥k
know. Only they know the secret key k. Now, they're gonna use a cipher which
只有他们知道密钥k，现在他们将使用密钥安全通信
consists of these two algorithms, E and D. E is called an encryption algorithm and D
这个密钥由E算法和D算法组成，E是加密算法
is called the decryption algorithm. The encryption algorithm takes the message and
D是解密算法，加密算法把信息和密钥作为输入
the key as inputs, and produces a corresponding ciphertext. And the
并生成对应的密文
decryption algorithm does the opposite. It takes the ciphertext as input along with the key
解密算法则正好相反，它以密文和密钥作为输入
key and produces the corresponding message. Now, a very important point that
并生成相应的明文信息，这里我要强调一点
I would like to stress. I'm only gonna say this once now and never again, but it is an
尽管它非常重要，但我只说一遍，不再重复
extremely important point. And that is: that the algorithms E and D, the actual
算法E，D，是向公众
encryption algorithms are publicly known. Adversary knows exactly how they work. The
公开的加密算法。攻击者是知道算法是怎么工作的
only thing that's kept secret is the secret key k. Other than that
只有密钥k是保密的
everything else is completely public and it's really important to realize that you
其他所有东西都是公开的，明白这点很重要
should only use algorithms that are public because those algorithms have been
你应该使用公开的加密算法
peer-reviewed by a very large community of hundreds of people for many, many, many years,
因为这种算法已经由数以百计的业内人士检查了很多很多年
and these algorithms only begin to be used once this community has shown that
而且只有算法被业内证实无法破解时，这个算法才能开始被使用
they cannot be broken, essentially. So in fact, if somebody comes to you and says, hey, I have a proprietary
事实，如果有个人跟你说，我有一个私人加密方法
cipher that you might want to use, the answer usually should be that
问你要不要试试，答案通常是
you stick to standards, to standard algorithms, and not use a proprietary
坚持使用标准算法，摒弃专有算法
cipher. In fact, there are many examples of proprietary ciphers that, as soon as
实际上，有很多专有加密算法的例子
they were reverse engineered, they were easily broken by simple analysis.
一旦他们被逆向工程法分析，很容易被分析破解
Now, even in the simple cases of symmetric encryption which we're gonna discuss
现在，即使是我们在前半部分讨论的对称加密的简单情况下，
in the first half of the course, there are actually two cases that we're gonna discuss in turn.
实际上也有两种情况，我们将逐一讨论。
The first, is when every key is only used to encrypt a
第一种，每个密钥只加密一个信息
single message, we call these one time keys. Okay. So for example, when you
我们称之为一次一密，例如
encrypt email messages, it's very common that every single email is encrypted using
当你加密邮件信息时，通常不同的邮件
a different symmetric key. Yeah? Different symmetric cipher key. Because the key is
使用不同的对称密钥加密，对吧？不同的对称密钥
used to encrypt only one message there are actually fairly efficient and simple ways of
因为一个密钥只加密一个信息
所以有很多加密方法
encrypting messages using these one time keys and we'll discuss those actually
非常有效和简洁地使用一次密钥加密信息
我们将在下一模块讨论这些方法
in the next module. Now there are many cases in fact where keys
实际上，有很多时候一个密钥需要加密多个信息
need to be used to encrypt multiple messages. We call these many time keys.
我们称这些为多次密钥
For example, when you encrypt files in a file system the same key is used
例如，在一个文件系统里用同一个密钥加密很多不同的文件
to encrypt many many, different files. And it turns out if the key is now going to be used to encrypt
事实证明如果用同一个密钥加密多个信息
multiple messages we need a little bit of more machinery to make sure that the
我们需要更多的机制来确保加密系统的安全
encryption system is secure. In fact after we talk about the one-time keys, we
事实上，在我们介绍了一次一密之后
will move over and talk about encryption modes that are specifically designed for
我们还将介绍专门为多次密钥设计的加密模式
many-time keys. And we'll see that there are a couple more steps that need to be taken to
我们将会看到为了确保信息安全采取的一系列步骤
ensure security in those cases. Okay, the last point I wanna make
好了，最后说一点
is that there are a couple of important things to remember about cryptography. First of all,
关于密码学有几点很重要，首先
cryptography, of course, is a fantastic tool for protecting information in computer systems.
密码学，是用来保护计算机系统中信息的一个很有效的工具
However, it's also very important that cryptography has its limitations.
然而，同样重要的是，密码学也有它的局限性
First of all, cryptography is really not the solution to all security problems.
首先，密码学不能解决所有安全问题
For example, if you have software bugs then very often cryptography is not
例如，如果你的软件经常出现bug
那么很可能密码学就帮不了你
going to be able to help you. Similarly, if you're worried about social engineering attacks,
类似的，如果你担心受到社会工程学攻击
where the attacker tries to fool the user into taking actions
例如攻击者试图欺骗用户去做会不利于用户的事
that are going to hurt the user, then cryptography is very often actually not
那么密码学也帮不了你r(st)q
going to help you. So it's very important that although it's a fabulous tool, it's not the
尽管密码学是极好的工具
solution to all security problems. Now another very important point is that cryptography
它也解决不了所有的安全问题，另外非常重要的一点是
essentially becomes useless if it's implemented incorrectly. So, for example,
如果没有正确地使用，密码学也将变为无用。例如
there are a number of systems that work perfectly fine. And we'll see examples of those
有很多系统在正常工作，我们会看到这些系统
systems, that, in fact, allow Alice and Bob to communicate. And,
允许Alice和Bob进行通信
in fact, messages that Alice sent to Bob, Bob can receive and decrypt. However,
实际上，Alice发送信息给Bob，Bob收到信息并解密
because cryptography is implemented incorrectly, the systems are completely insecure.
但是，由于密码学被不当使用，系统实际上非常的不安全
Actually I should say that I like to mention an old encryption standard
这里我应该提及一个古老的加密标准WEP
called WEP this is used for encrypting Wi-Fi traffic. WEP contains many
WEP用来加密WiFi流量，WEP有很多的错误。
mistakes in it and often when I wanna show you how not to do things in cryptography
经常我在课上给你们演示在密码学里什么事不能做的时候
I will point to how things were done in WEP as an example. So for me, it's very fortunate to have an example,
我就会以WEP的内容为例，所以对于我来说，有这样的一个例子很幸运
a protocol I can point to for how not to do things. And finally, a very
一个可以指出什么不该做的案例，最后
important point that I'd like you to remember is that cryptography is not
很重要的一点请记住，密码学不是让
something you should try to invent and design yourself. As I said, there are
你自己设计发明。正如我所说
standards in cryptography, standard cryptographic primitives which we're gonna discuss
密码学有自己的标准，我们将会在这门课程中详细讨论
at length during this course. And primarily you're supposed to use
这些标准化的密码学原型。你只需要使用这些标准密码原型
these standard cryptographic primitives, and not invent things, these primitives,
不是发明它们
yourself. The standards have all gone through, many years of
这些原型已经经历了数年来人们的检测
review by hundreds of people, and that's not something that's going to happen to an ad hoc  design.
它们不是随意设计的
And, as I said, over the years there are many examples of
正如我所说，许多年来
ad hoc designs that were immediately broken as soon as they were analyzed.
许多随意设计的加密机制一经分析就立刻被破解。